John Chamberlain Papers
John Chamberlain Papers
1957-1967
Chamberlain, John, 1903-1995.
13 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, journalist, syndicated columnist (King Features Syndicate). Includes correspondence (1963-1967); manuscript drafts, notes for books and columns; research material; photographs; press releases.
148894
Biographical History
John Chamberlain was a syndicated columnist and was in contact with many public personalities including former president Richard Nixon.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Chamberlain Papers is composed of four series. Correspondence contains incoming and outgoing correspondence, including a signed letter from Richard Nixon. Writings contains books, research material, press releases, columns and related material, as well as a second signed letter from Nixon. The collection concludes with a few Photographs and some Miscellaneous material.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Writings are arranged by type; research material and ideas are arranged alphabetically while press releases are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Chamberlain, John, 1903-1995 Archives.; King Features Syndicate.; Authors, American.; Journalism, Authorship.; Journalists, United States.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Authors.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Chamberlain, 1967, 1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1963, Nixon letter is in folder 12; 12 folders (Box 1)
  - 1964, 13 folders (Box 2)
  - 1964, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1965, 8 folders (Box 3)
  - 1965 (Box 4)
  - 1966, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - 1967, 3 folders (Box 4)
- Writings
  - Books
    - Rough drafts
      - History of American Business, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - The Roots of Capitalism, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Columns and related material
    - Research material
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous, 11 folders (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous, 12 folders (Box 6)
    - Ideas
      - Miscellaneous, 12 folders (Box 7)
      - Balance of payments (Box 8)
      - Church and socialism (Box 8)
      - Common market (Box 8)
      - Cost of living (Box 8)
      - Ecology (Box 8)
      - Ford, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Foreign trade, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Libertarian lists (Box 8)
      - Log exports (Box 8)
      - Politics, 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Profit motive (Box 8)
      - Public power (Box 8)
      - Quality of life (Box 8)
      - Religion and schools (Box 8)
      - Republican Party (Box 8)
      - Smith, Grace (Box 8)
      - South, 1965 (Box 8)
      - Sports (Box 8)
      - Standard Oil (Box 8)
      - Steel (Box 8)
      - Taxes (Box 8)
      - Technology (Box 8)
      - Turn of the Wheel (Box 8)
      - War and education (Box 8)
    - Press releases
      - undated, 7 folders (Box 9)
      - 1963, Jan-Apr, Jun-Dec, 11 folders (Box 9)
      - 1964, Jan-Feb, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1964, Mar-Dec, 10 folders (Box 10)
      - 1965, Jan-May, Jul, 6 folders (Box 10)
      - 1965, Sep-Dec, Nixon letter in October; 4 folders (Box 11)
      - 1966, Jan-Jun, 8 folders (Box 11)
      - 1966, Jul-Nov, 5 folders (Box 12)
      - 1967, Jan-Dec, 13 folders (Box 12)
    - Booklets
      - The Freeman, 1957-1967; 84 volumes (Box 12)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Oversize 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous material (Oversize 1)